<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heraclitus Derisus, or, Ben's monkey stript by Sim and Sam</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13016556</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13016556</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43358)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 741:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heraclitus Derisus, or, Ben's monkey stript by Sim and Sam</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.D.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Broadside.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>A satire.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Anecdotes</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:96548:1"/>
            <head>HERACLIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S DERIS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, <hi>OR, BEN's Monkey Stript BY SIM AND SAM</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>YOU Sir, that go as though your Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding was o're-ſet with deep Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, about Cutting a New Road to the</hi> Antipodes; <hi>Or as if your Conſcience had got a ſharp Set of Teeth, and did begin to Bite Home; What they ſay you have been to ſee how</hi> Calvin<hi>'s Poſterity thrive, and to take a Pattern of that Government, that you may be the more Exact in Cutting out one here, then you were heretofore; Come,</hi> Ben<hi>'s</hi> Monkey <hi>knew well that you were gone to take one Cup of</hi> Presbytery; <hi>a late Puppy-dog of his Brains g<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve ſhrewd Hints at your going away.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Why, this 'tis now, a Siſter cannot be abſent, but you preſently ſay her Nature was Gravid, and ſhe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to let ſlip; And a Brother cannot be abſent; but you ſay he is Run the Countrey; But I have not been out of this Nation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But you have Chang'd your Lodging; Were you Remov'd by</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>or</hi> Certiorari?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>By neither; for I was in truth led away in one of your Proteſtant Wheel-Barrows; But pray ſhut up that malevolous Skull of yours, and not ſcatter ſo much Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as hitherto you have done, to the great diſturbance of the well-affected people, that have now digeſted all fears of the Horrid Plot; and may have their Throats cut and not know of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Very well; That's a pretty way of leaving the World; but where haſt been? I have diligently ſought thee; I have beat all the Buſhes in</hi> Whetſtones Park; <hi>Nay, to be ſure I was at all our fine Shews of Religion, ſor I did not know but that thou might'ſt have had a Mind to two or three penniworth of Zeal; I was at the</hi> Family of Love, <hi>and at</hi> Maſs <hi>too; where I ſaw ſuch ſport, that indeed I thought I was at the Duke's</hi> Play-houſe; <hi>But I could not have the leaſt ſmatch of thee; I have highly wanted thy Company to mince the State a little in our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as we were uſed to do.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>I know well that the Sagacity of your Snout is very excellent, but I think I was now beyond the Reach of your Noſtrils; but pray forbear all Fanatical Diſcourſe, I have a Garment on call'd <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi> that is, to ſpeak Vulgarly, I am Chang'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What turn'd</hi> Tory, <hi>Indeed you ſmell of Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary power; Tack about as well as Major</hi> Waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot; <hi>but where haſt thou been?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>A Ship-board.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>A Ship-board, on ſome Land-Frigat I'le war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you; and you preſently got down to her Hold, I believe; You are a diveliſh Rogue thereabouts, What is ſhe call'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Truly ſhe is a Land-Frigat, for ſhe never did yet Sail beyond <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, but ſhe hath done great Service againſt the Geneva-Pirates; She is call'd, <hi>The Loyal Benjamin.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>But how is it, that you who have been as deep a Whig as any, ſhould now become a very handſom Nitid Tory?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>VVhy, go to the next Tavern, I'le give you an Exact <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Reformation of my Members.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>Agreed Sir, with all my Heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Here Drawer, Bring us a Bottle of rare Royal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Wine; ſuch as will make a Man leap over <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum-Steeple</hi> for the King, and a Chamber Pot that's well-affected to the Government, for I cannot <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinate in any Seditious Veſſels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>Fine parts indeed, but not Conſonant to the Capacities of our Whiggiſh Femalites; but pray Sir, draw out your Hiſtory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>VVell Sir, give Ear; ſome time ſince I was at that honeſt Tavern of yours, where the Proteſtant Quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence of the Town, I mean thoſe Youths of Policy and Contrivance, that are uſed to Meet every Night at the <hi>Kings Head,</hi> to Toſs the Government in a Blanket, where I took a Bottle of Liberty and Property, and ſo came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as I thought, a very high Proteſtant; but as I was Marching, I was on a ſudden Seiz'd on; now for fear I ſhould be <hi>Arnold-liz'd,</hi> I began to vociferate extreamly; but the <hi>Seizor</hi> ſaid, that Exclamation was altogether ſuperfluous, for there was no other deſign againſt me, but only to Cure me of a Diſeaſe, now very Epidemical, call'd <hi>Sedition;</hi> then Sir, by I know not what force I was Mounted up ſome Seven or Eight Pair of Grades, and there laid at his VVittineſs<hi>'s Sir Ridens's</hi> Feet, for you muſt know that he is a Man of a Phariſaical Scull, and nothing could Gratifie his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, but the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Room in the <hi>Houſe;</hi> Well, and what's next?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How the Devil ſhould I know, I never kept Company with</hi> Phariſees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Then he Commanded that I ſhould be Stript, that he might have a Proſpect of me <hi>in puris Naturalibus;</hi> And when he had viewed me a while, he did Opine from the diſaffected Spots, and infectious Scabs that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, that my Sanguineous Maſs was much Vitiated with the Heterogeneous Particles of Schiſm and Sedition, and my <hi>Sal, Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> were falling into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>An excellent Quack indeed; pray deſire him to feel the Pulſe of State too, and give her a Pill, for ſhe highly wants purging.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Why he intends it, you ſhall hear of it a Chapter or two hence; but let me go on, He bid me open my Mouth, which I did though I told him the Mark was out, and from under my Tongue he pull<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a great Bag of Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which he ſaid was the cauſe why I foamed ſo much Malignity againſt the State; Afterwards I was laid all along on one-ſide as if I was going to be ſerved as you do Sows in the Countrey when you pull out their <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery</hi> by the Roots, but it ſeems it was only to take out my <hi>Gall,</hi> which he did with ſo much dexterity, that I think he hath Rode round the Nation with a Horn at his Girdle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſeems you have been Spay'd, and this Spark is Sow-Gelder to the Government; But this was dangerous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:96548:2"/>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Not for a Man of Art, for be hadſpread a Plaiſter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Gooſe-greaſe,</hi> which he had ſcraped off from the Fat Quoife of ſome well-fed Parſon, and clos'd the Orifice preſently, then I was put into Bed, where by the help of ſome ſpiritual Sudorificks, I fell into a great Sweat, and I think I may now ſay, I am abſterg'd from all Purulency both of Fleſh and Spirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>Now you have ſeen this famous One, pray is the Figure of the Fool well imitated in the Draught we had at the Elephant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>There is a little Reſemblance, but ſome remarkable Parts about him are not well drawn; As for inſtance, he had a Noſe exceeding big, ſo that I thought he might have come Home one Night with an intoxicated <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and have Run it againſt the City-Poſt he told us of, but I was miſtaken, for he ſaid he went on purpoſe to the <hi>Glaſs-houſe,</hi> to have it blown up to that Magnitude, that the Ladies might think he had a good Bag of Virility in his Codpiſt; He had an immenſe Heap of Fleſh in his Back, ſo that I did fancy one of his Moles had been a Working, and rais'd a Hillock; and that his Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Inſects would build a Common-wealth on his Shoulders; I asked him a bold Queſtion or two, <hi>Whether ſome of his Ancients were not of an</hi> African <hi>ſtrain? Or whether he was not deſcended from the Ancient Family of the Camels?</hi> He ſaid, <hi>No, but that he was a Man over-ſtock'd with Loyalty, and not having Vent for it, it ran up into that immoderate Protu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berancy.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>A very well built Beaſt; But we have had a Change here too, for all our Proteſtant News Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants are all broken or ſuppreſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>No, they have Run themſelves down, for it ſeems they would Vent none but what was highly Protestant, and their Veſſels being well Exhauſted, it would not look well to ſetforth their <hi>Lees; What then, no News-Jobbers?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, well-affected</hi> Nath. <hi>continues ſtill, and comes out twice a Week, with his Half-ſheet of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; He Tickles the Tails of the diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; He is Reſolved to Whip them into the pale of the Church; He is of the ſame uſe to our Holy Guides as a Dog is to a Shepherd; he brings in the ſtragling ones to the Fold.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Who I pray, is this well affected <hi>Nath?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Fetter-lane <hi>Spark, a Haberdaſher of ſmall Wares, one that deals in Letters, Syllables and Words; he hath likewiſe a good ſtore of Bum-fod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by him, ſo that he can do your Breech a kindneſs at any time.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Is his News true?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>As true as the Holy See it ſelf, not a ſtroke of Falſhoods in his whole paper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad we are ſerv'd with one honeſt Man, now no more Noiſe of horrid Plots.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh, you would think by his News, that there never was a Plot, or that the Sun had ſo dried it, that it was turned to ſome Jeſuits powder; beſides, he is a Man of Superfine parts, for he can Raiſe from the Dead, he lately Raiſed an Act of Parliament; Nay Sir, if your Wife hath bin dead theſe twenty years, ſo that her Atoms are Tranſmigrated into other Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and you deſire her once more, Repair but to this</hi> Nath. <hi>the</hi> Necromancer, <hi>and he by Virtue of a</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Whiſtle <hi>can Recal all diſperſed parts, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite them in their firſt pleaſant plump</hi> Compoſitum; <hi>Nay, ſhe ſhall make you as good ſport, as ſhe did when you firſt joyn'd her Pan of Procreation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>Very brave, ſure he will be a Saint before he goes to Heaven?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Si.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We make many, a little without</hi> Holbourn; <hi>But now you talk of it let's Toſs a Query,</hi> Whether it is not high time that <hi>Ben's Monkey</hi> and <hi>Nath's</hi> ſhould be quarter'd up into Saints? <hi>I mean,</hi> Whether it would not be handſom for theſe two Loyal Loggerheads to Ride <hi>Skimmington</hi> on <hi>Tyburn?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <p>I'le Anſwer you the next time, Farewell.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>Theſe are to Certiſie our <hi>Tadpole Tories,</hi> That if their <hi>Tantivyſhips</hi> are able to Purchaſe New Cloaths this Spring, they may be Provided with very Faſhionable Buttons, that were made by the Breech of Mr. <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator,</hi> alias, <hi>R. Runaway</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> when the Parliament made him Fly for <hi>Flanders;</hi> And are to be ſold by his Old Friend <hi>de Henrico Bromano,</hi> who is to have the Benefit of his <hi>Breech,</hi> as well as of his <hi>Brain.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. D.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
